<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN'
'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0b5/dtd/docbook.dtd'
>
<section xml:id="basic-architecture" version="5.0"
xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Jetty 7 Architecture</title>
  <section>
    <title>View from 20,000 feet</title>
    <para>The Jetty Server is the plumbing between a collection of Connectors
    that accept HTTP connections, and a collection of Handlers that service
    requests from the connections and produce responses, with the work being
    done by threads taken from a thread pool.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <info>
        <othercredit>
          <orgname>jetty simple high level architecture</orgname>
        </othercredit>
      </info>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" width="6in" format="PNG"
        fileref="images/jetty-high-level-architecture.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>While the jetty request/responses are derived from the Servlet API,
    the full features of the servlet API are only available if the appropriate
    handlers are configured. For example, the session API on the request is
    inactive unless the request has been passed to a Session Handler. The
    concept of a Servlet itself is implemented by a Servlet Handler. If
    servlets are not required, there is very little overhead in the use of the
    servlet request/response APIs. Thus you can build a Jetty server using only
    connectors and handlers, without using Servlets.</para>
    <para>The job of configuring jetty is the job of building a network of
    connectors and handlers and providing their individual configurations. As
    Jetty components are simply Plain Old Java Objects (POJOs), you can
    accomplish this assembly and configuration of components by a variety of
    techniques:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>In code. See the examples in the Jetty 7 Latest Source
      XRef.</listitem>
      <listitem>With Jetty XML - dependency injection style XML
      format.</listitem>
      <listitem>With your dependency injection framework of choice: Spring or
      XBean.</listitem>
      <listitem>Using Jetty WebApp and Context Deployers.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
