<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
//  ========================================================================
//  Copyright (c) 1995-2012 Mort Bay Consulting Pty. Ltd.
//  ========================================================================
//  All rights reserved. This program and the accompanying materials
//  are made available under the terms of the Eclipse Public License v1.0
//  and Apache License v2.0 which accompanies this distribution.
//
//      The Eclipse Public License is available at
//      http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html
//
//      The Apache License v2.0 is available at
//      http://www.opensource.org/licenses/apache2.0.php
//
//  You may elect to redistribute this code under either of these licenses.
//  ========================================================================
-->
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
         xml:id="contributing-patches" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Contributing Patches</title>

  <para>How to contribute a patch to the jetty project. You should first
  familiarize yourself with the Eclipse wiki page on <link
  xl:href="http://wiki.eclipse.org/Development_Resources/Contributing_via_Git">contributing
  via Git</link>.</para>

  <section xml:id="contributing-cla">
    <title>Sign a CLA</title>

    <para>The Eclipse Foundation has a strong Intellectual Property policy
    which tracks contributions in detail to ensure that:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Did the contributor author 100% of the content?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Does the contributor have the rights to contribute this content
        to Eclipse?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Is the contribution under the project’s license(s) (e.g.
        EPL)</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Thus a contributor needs to e-sign a <link xl:href="???">Contributor
    Licence Agreement</link> (for more explanation see the <link
    xl:href="http://www.eclipse.org/legal/clafaq.php">Eclipse CLA FAQ</link> )
    regardless of how their contribution patch is provided.</para>

    <tip>
      <title>Signing an Eclipse CLA</title>

      <para>Log into the <link
      xl:href="https://projects.eclipse.org/user/login/sso">Eclipse projects
      forge</link> (you will need to create an account with the Eclipse
      Foundation if you have not already done so); click on "Contributor
      License Agreement"; and Complete the form. Be sure to use the same email
      address when you create any Git commit records.</para>
    </tip>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>GitHub Contribution</title>

    <para>Jetty is hosted at GitHub and accepts pull requests now.  However you 
    must have a CLA on file as mentioned above, with the email address you will 
    be using at github for your signed commit.  Make sure your commit is using 
    the email that you registered in your CLA or no amount of pushing the in 
    world from us will get past the eclipse git commit hooks. When you do your 
    commit that you use for the pull request it is
    also <emphasis>vital</emphasis> that you "sign-off" on the commit using
    "git commit -s". Without the sign-off, your patch cannot be applied to the
    jetty repo because it will be rejected.</para>

    <para>One way to think of this is that when you sign the CLA you are 
    indicating that you are free to contribute to eclipse, but that doesn't
    mean everything you ever do can be contributed.  Using the commit signing
    mechanism indicates that your commit is under the auspices of your 
    agreement.</para>

  </section>
</section>
