<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
//  ========================================================================
//  Copyright (c) 1995-2012 Mort Bay Consulting Pty. Ltd.
//  ========================================================================
//  All rights reserved. This program and the accompanying materials
//  are made available under the terms of the Eclipse Public License v1.0
//  and Apache License v2.0 which accompanies this distribution.
//
//      The Eclipse Public License is available at
//      http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html
//
//      The Apache License v2.0 is available at
//      http://www.opensource.org/licenses/apache2.0.php
//
//  You may elect to redistribute this code under either of these licenses.
//  ========================================================================
-->
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd"
         xml:id="contributing-patches" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Contributing Patches</title>

  <para>How to contribute a patch to the jetty project. You should first
  familiarize yourself with the Eclipse wiki page on <link
  xl:href="http://wiki.eclipse.org/Development_Resources/Contributing_via_Git">contributing
  via Git</link>.</para>

  <section xml:id="contributing-cla">
    <title>Sign a CLA</title>

    <para>The Eclipse Foundation has a strong Intellectual Property policy
    which tracks contributions in detail to ensure that:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Did the contributor author 100% of the content?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Does the contributor have the rights to contribute this content
        to Eclipse?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Is the contribution under the project’s license(s) (e.g.
        EPL)</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Thus a contributor needs to e-sign a <link xl:href="???">Contributor
    Licence Agreement</link> (for more explanation see the <link
    xl:href="http://www.eclipse.org/legal/clafaq.php">Eclipse CLA FAQ</link> )
    regardless of how their contribution patch is provided.</para>

    <tip>
      <title>Signing an Eclipse CLA</title>

      <para>Log into the <link
      xl:href="https://projects.eclipse.org/user/login/sso">Eclipse projects
      forge</link> (you will need to create an account with the Eclipse
      Foundation if you have not already done so); click on "Contributor
      License Agreement"; and Complete the form. Be sure to use the same email
      address when you create any Git commit records.</para>
    </tip>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Use Bugzilla</title>

    <para>Once a CLA has been signed, then patches should always be
    contributed with an associated <link xl:href="???">project
    bugzilla</link>. The CLA symbol next to the contributors name in the
    bugzilla should be green to indicate the CLA is on record. This will allow
    the authors contribution to both be tracked and acknowledged.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="git-diff">
    <title>Git Diff</title>

    <para>The simplest way to contribute a patch is to make a modification to
    a cloned copy of jetty and then generate a diff between the two versions.
    We don't really like this approach, but it is difficult to ignore how easy
    it is for the contributer. Just remember, you still need to create a CLA
    as mentioned above.</para>

    <para>From the top level of the cloned project:</para>

    <screen><![CDATA[      
$ git diff > ######.patch

]]></screen>

    <para>The hash marks should be the bugzilla issue that you will be
    attaching the issue to. All patches coming into jetty must come in through
    bugzilla for IP tracking purposes, even if they are coming in as commits
    through gerrit. Depending on the size of the patch the patch itself may be
    flagged as +iplog where it is subject to lawyer review and inclusion with
    our iplog from here to eternity. We are sorry we are unable to apply
    patches that we receive via email. So if you have the bugzilla issue
    created already just attach the issue and feel free to bug us on <xref
        linkend="community-irc">
         IRC 
      </xref> to take a look. If there is no bugzilla issue yet, create one,
    make sure the patch is named appropriately and attach it.</para>

    <para>When the developer reviews the patch and goes to apply it they will
    use:</para>

    <screen><![CDATA[      
$ git apply < ######.patch

]]></screen>

    <para>If you want to be a nice person, test your patch on a clean clone to
    ensure that it applies cleanly. Nothing frustrates a developer quite like
    a patch that doesn't apply.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>RECOMMENDED - Git Format Patch</title>

    <para>Another approach if you want your name in shiny lights in our commit
    logs is to use the format patch option. With this approach you commit into
    your cloned copy of jetty and use the git format patch option to generate
    what looks like an email message containing all of the commit information.
    This applies as a commit directly when we apply it so it should be obvious
    that as with the normal diff we must accept these sorts of patches only
    via bugzilla. Make sure your commit is using the email that you registered
    in your CLA or no amount of pushing the in world from us will get past the
    eclipse git commit hooks. When you do your commit to your local repo it is
    also <emphasis>vital</emphasis> that you "sign-off" on the commit using
    "git commit -s". Without the sign-off, your patch cannot be applied to the
    jetty repo because it will be rejected by the eclipse git commit
    hooks.</para>

    <para>From the top level of the cloned project:</para>

    <para>Make your changes and commit them locally using <code>git commit
    -s</code>:</para>

    <screen><![CDATA[      
$ git commit -s
 ]]></screen>

    <para>Then use git log to identify the commit(s) you want to include in
    your patch:</para>

    <screen><![CDATA[      
commit 70e29326fe904675f772b88a67128c0b3529565e
Author: John Doe <john.doe@who.com>
      Date: Tue Aug 2 14:36:50 2011 +0200 353563:
HttpDestinationQueueTest too slow
    ]]></screen>

    <para>Use git format-patch to create the patch:</para>

    <screen><![CDATA[      
$ git format-patch -M -B 70e29326fe904675f772b88a67128c0b3529565e
 ]]></screen>

    <para>This will create a single patch file for each commit since the
    specified commit. The names will start with 0001-[commitmessage].patch.
    See http://www.kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/git-format-patch.html
    for details.</para>

    <para>When a developer goes to apply this sort of patch then we must
    assume responsibility for applying it to our codebase from the IP
    perspective. So we must be comfortable with the providence of the patch
    and that it is clear of potential issues. This is not like a diff where
    you get to edit it and clean up issues before it gets applied. The commit
    is recorded locally and the developer will then have a chance to make
    additional commits to address any lingering issues. It is critically
    important that developers applying these sorts of patches are fully aware
    of what is being committed and what they are accepting.</para>

    <para>To apply the patch the developer will use a command like:</para>

    <screen><![CDATA[    
$ git am 0001-353563-HttpDestinationQueueTest-too-slow.patch
 ]]></screen>

    <para>Providing it applies cleanly there will now be a commit in their
    local copy and they can either make additional commits or push it
    out.</para>

    <para><note>
        <para>It is intended that developers are also able to counter-sign the
        patch by using the '-s' option with the 'git am' command. However as
        the git hook that processes the commit currently has a bug it is
        recommended that developers do NOT use the -s option. See <link
        xl:href="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=415307">https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=415307</link></para>
      </note></para>

    <section xml:id="git-amend">
      <title>Git Amend</title>

      <para>If a committer is having trouble applying the patch cleanly with
      git am, they can use git commit --amend to modify the author and signoff
      the commit. For example:</para>

      <screen><![CDATA[      
$ git checkout -b patch
$ git apply john-doe.patch
$ git commit -a -m "<Original commit message from John Doe>"
    ]]></screen>

      <para>At this point the patch is committed with the committer's name on
      a local branch</para>

      <screen><![CDATA[      
$ git commit --amend --author "John Doe <john.doe@who.com>" --signoff
    ]]></screen>

      <para>Now the patch has the right author and it has been signed
      off</para>

      <screen><![CDATA[      
$ git checkout master
$ git merge patch
 ]]></screen>

      <para>Now the local branch has been merged into master with the right
      author</para>

      <screen><![CDATA[      
$ git branch -d patch
$ git push
 ]]></screen>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Contributing with Gerrit</title>

    <para><link xl:href="https://wiki.eclipse.org/Gerrit">Gerrit</link> is a
    web based code review system, facilitating online code reviews for
    projects using the Git version control system.</para>

    <section xml:id="gerrit-for-contributors">
      <title>Gerrit for Contributors</title>

      <para>Prepare yourself for using gerrit by following the steps described
      here: <link
      xl:href="https://git.eclipse.org/r/Documentation/user-upload.html">https://git.eclipse.org/r/Documentation/user-upload.html</link></para>

      <para>Then clone the jetty-project:</para>

      <screen><![CDATA[    
$ git clone ssh://git.eclipse.org:29418/jetty/org.eclipse.jetty.project
     ]]></screen>

      <para><emphasis>Stop.</emphasis> Make sure you have a bugzilla issue
      open for the change that you want to commit into gerrit for review. Also
      when you are ready to commit your change make sure that your commit
      starts with the bugzilla id. For example your commit should look like
      this:</para>

      <screen><![CDATA[     
$ git commit -m "[Bug 343532] fixed issue" <files>

]]></screen>

      <para>Make sure to properly set the changeIds as described here: <link
      xl:href="https://git.eclipse.org/r/Documentation/user-changeid.html">https://git.eclipse.org/r/Documentation/user-changeid.html</link></para>

      <para>Make your changes, commit them as usual with git. Once done
      do:</para>

      <screen><![CDATA[    
$ git push ssh://git.eclipse.org:29418/jetty/org.eclipse.jetty.project HEAD:refs/for/master

]]></screen>

      <para>Note the magic: <code>HEAD:refs/for/master</code>. Without gerrit
      will not permit you to push.</para>

      <para>Review your changes on your gerrit dashboard: <link
      xl:href="https://git.eclipse.org/r/#/">https://git.eclipse.org/r/#/</link></para>

      <para>Finally get some coffee and relax. You've contributed something to
      jetty, woohooo. :)</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="gerrit-for-committers">
      <title>Gerrit for Committers</title>

      <para>Using gerrit is pretty simple. Once you have logged in you should
      first register your interest in the project repositories you want to be
      notified of patches on. This option is located under your user Settings
      near your name in the upper right hand corner. Click on 'Watched
      Projects' and then start typing 'jetty' into the project name box and it
      will offer completions for the jetty projects.</para>

      <para>Now that you are watching the appropriate projects you should get
      email notifications of commits into gerrit. It is critical that you
      follow strict committer IP process when reviewing commits. Egregious
      violations of this process can result in committer status issues.</para>

      <para>On the top of the screen click My -&gt; Watched Changes for a list
      of the commits available for review. These represent people waiting to
      have their work reviewed. Once you select an issue to review you will
      see a list of changes at the bottom, click on these and look over the
      changes. You can have a dialog back and forth with the user through the
      comments on the patch. Providing they used the ChangeId setup correctly
      they will be able to issue updates to their patch for further review.
      Once you are happy with a review change set click on the Review button.
      This brings up a screen with three important questions.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Verified</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Have you verified if this patch is acceptable.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Code Review</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How acceptable is this review change set? Are you willing to
            testitfy that it is good enough or does it bear further
            review.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>IP Clean</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Does this commit follow acceptable IP guidelines? If
            anything looks suspicious then follow up with comments to clarify
            any potential issues. Commits with minor changes to existing
            classes and projects are fine and should reference a corresponding
            bugzilla id in their commit message.</para>

            <para>Completely new features and large contributions require a
            corresponding CQ reference.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Assuming sufficient approval through the review process there will
      be an option to Review and Submit and the commit will pass through into
      jetty proper. You may also review and comment without submitting so the
      Review button is useful for clearly stating the reviewers comments and
      concerns regarding the three items mentioned above. Multiple reviewers
      are able to collaborate on a given patch as well.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Contributing via GitHub PullRequests</title>

    <para>The jetty eclipse git repository is mirrored to github at <link
    xl:href="https://github.com/eclipse/jetty.project">http://github.com/eclipse/jetty.project</link>.
    Github has a suite of collaboration tools for submitting and reviewing
    contributions, but unfortunately the Eclipse Foundations IP policy
    prevents direct merging of github pull requests. However, if a contributor
    makes a pull request and references that in a bugzilla with a signed CLA,
    then a Jetty committer should be able to fetch, merge and commit the pull
    requests without the need to create a separate patch.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Github pull requests for Committers</title>

      <para>A committer can prepare their repository for accepting Github pull
      requests as follows:</para>

      <screen><![CDATA[$ git remote add github https://github.com/eclipse/jetty.project.git
$ git config --add remote.github.fetch "+refs/pull/*/head:refs/remotes/origin/pr/*"]]></screen>

      <para>A committer can then fetch the latest pull request and check them
      out as follows (for pull request #123):</para>

      <screen><![CDATA[$ git fetch github
$ git checkout pr/123]]></screen>

      <para>The committer can then use normal git commands to merge the
      contribution back to the master branch. The commits may need to be
      signed off so they can be pushed using the git amend technique
      above.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
