<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="introduction" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">
  <title>Introducing Jetty</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <info>
      <othercredit>
        <orgname>jetty logo</orgname>
      </othercredit>
    </info>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata align="center" width="6in" format="GIF" fileref="images/jetty.gif" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <section>
    <title>What is Jetty?</title>
    <para>Jetty is an open-source project providing an HTTP server, HTTP client, and javax.servlet container. This
    document is broken into two parts. The first part has an emphasis on beginning to use jetty from the context on the
    distribution. It will provides information about downloading Jetty, basic configuration on how to change things
    like the port jetty runs on and adjusting logging levels and configuring many of the most common servlet container
    features like JNDI, JMX and session management. The second part of this document describes advanced usages of
    jetty, specific indepth features like our highly scalable async client, proxy servlet configuration, or configuring
    the jetty maven plugin or using jetty as an embedded server. The advanced section will include tutorials, howtos,
    videos, and some reference materials.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>What version do I use?</title>
    <para>Jetty 9 is the most recent version of Jetty and has a great many improvements over the previous versions. One
    improvement being this documentation which is focused on Jetty 9. While many people continue to use older versions
    of Jetty we generally recommend using Jetty 9 as it represents the version of Jetty that we will actively maintain
    and improve over the next few years.</para>
    <para>For a bit of historical context, Jetty 6 was a major rewrite of Jetty over Jetty 5 and was the lead supported
    version of Jetty for many years. Near the end of the life of Jetty 6 the project was moved to the Eclipse
    Foundation and Jetty 7 and Jetty 8 were born out of that migration. At the time there were significant changes
    between Jetty 6 and Jetty 7, most noticiably the improvement of the maven build coupled with a large artifact
    reorganiation, and the obvious package name changes required from the move to Eclipse. Initially the hope that been
    that this would coincide with the release of the Servlet 3.0 spec but that ended up being delayed, which meant the
    migration to eclipse would continue supporting Servlet 2.5 and Jetty 8 was born once that spec landed. Since Jetty
    6 and 7 has supported many of the fundamentals of the Servlet 3.0 spec (namely async servlets) we decided that we
    would release 7 and 8 in lockstep which is why the release dates for Jetty 7 and 8 always match up.</para>
    <para>In a similar situation, we were waiting on the Servlet 3.1 spec to be released before we jumped to Jetty 9
    but once more events conspired against this and we will instead be updating Jetty 9 to 9.1 once that spec is
    released. We will continue to support Jetty 7 and 8 in maintanence mode for the next couple of years but Jetty 9 is
    where it is at as it were.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
