<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
//  ========================================================================
//  Copyright (c) 1995-2012 Mort Bay Consulting Pty. Ltd.
//  ========================================================================
//  All rights reserved. This program and the accompanying materials
//  are made available under the terms of the Eclipse Public License v1.0
//  and Apache License v2.0 which accompanies this distribution.
//
//      The Eclipse Public License is available at
//      http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html
//
//      The Apache License v2.0 is available at
//      http://www.opensource.org/licenses/apache2.0.php
//
//  You may elect to redistribute this code under either of these licenses.
//  ========================================================================
-->
<section version="5.0" 
  xml:id="cloudfoundry"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">
  <title>CloudFoundry</title>
  <para>
    This buildpack is quite simple to use. It is currently hard coded to a specific Jetty version of 9.0.1.v20130408 and to change that the apparent approach is to simply fork this buildpack and tweak that directly. To do this simply fork it in GitHub and tweak the JETTY_VERSION string in the jetty_web.rb file.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you have modifications to make to the Jetty server that will be running, like perhaps configuring additional static contexts, setting up a proxy servlet, adding items to the jetty.home/lib/ext directory, you can either adapt the ruby scripting or place them under the appropriate location in the resources directory of this buildpack and they will be copied into the correct location.
  </para>
  <para>
    The new CloudFoundry buildpacks seem to be very simple to use and straightforward to setup and customize. However customize seems to be a really key component so I am unsure how relevant this buildpack will be outside of serving as root fork for customized jetty buildpack, or just a simple example of how to do one of your own for CloudFoundry.
  </para>
  <para>
    Feel free to submit feedback via normal github channels and I'll accept pull requests on this should they come.
  </para>
  <para>
    For the time being I'll leave this buildpack under my personal github account and should there be interest expressed I am more then happy to push it over to https://github.com/jetty-project down the road for proper contributions, etc.
  </para>

  <section xml:id="cloudfoundry-acknowledgements">
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>
    <para>
      The Jetty buildpack was forked from the CloudFoundry Java buildpack. I looked at the Virgo Buildpack that Glyn worked on as a sanity check.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>          
          <link xl:href="http://github.com/cloudfoundry/cloudfoundry-buildpack-java">http://github.com/cloudfoundry/cloudfoundry-buildpack-java</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>          
          <link xl:href="http://github.com/glyn/virgo-buildpack">http://github.com/glyn/virgo-buildpack</link>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      CloudFoundry buildpacks were modelled on Heroku buildpacks.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
