<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN'
'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0b5/dtd/docbook.dtd'
>
<section xml:id="contributing-patches" version="5.0"
xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
xmlns:mth="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Contributing Patches</title>
  <para>How to contribute a patch to the jetty project.</para>
  <section xml:id="git-diff">
    <title>Git Diff</title>
    <para>The simplest way to contribute a patch is to make a modification to a
    cloned copy of jetty and then generate a diff between the two
    versions.</para>
    <para>From the top level of the cloned project:</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git diff < ######.patch
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>The hash marks should be the bugzilla issue that you will be
    attaching the issue to. All patches coming into jetty @ eclipse much come
    in through bugzilla for IP tracking purposes. Depending on the size of the
    patch the patch itself may be flagged as +iplog where it is subject to
    lawyer review and inclusion with our iplog from here to eternity. We are
    sorry we are unable to apply patches that we receive via email. So if you
    have the bugzilla issue created already just attach the issue and feel free
    to bug us on IRC to take a look. If there is no bugzilla issue yet, create
    one, make sure the patch is named appropriately and attach it.</para>
    <para>When the developer reviews the patch and goes to apply it they will
    use:</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git apply < ######.patch
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>If you want to be a nice person, test your patch on a clean clone to
    ensure that it applies cleanly. Nothing frustrated a developer quite like a
    patch that doesn't apply.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Git Format Patch</title>
    <para>Another approach if you want your name in shiny lights in our commit
    logs is to use the format patch option. With this approach you commit into
    your cloned copy of jetty and use the git format patch option to generate
    what looks like an email message containing all of the commit information.
    This applies as a commit directly when we apply it so it should be obvious
    that as with the normal diff we much accept these sorts of patching only
    via bugzilla.</para>
    <para>From the top level of the cloned project:</para>
    <para>Make your changes and commit them locally using git commit. Then use
    git log to identify the commit(s) you want to include in your patch:</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
commit 70e29326fe904675f772b88a67128c0b3529565e
Author: John Doe <john.doe@who.com>
Date: Tue Aug 2 14:36:50 2011 +0200 353563:
HttpDestinationQueueTest too slow
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>Use git format-patch to create the patch:</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git format-patch -M -B 70e29326fe904675f772b88a67128c0b3529565e
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>This will create a single patch file for each commit since the
    specified commit. The names will start with 0001-[commitmessage].patch. See
    http://www.kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/git-format-patch.html for
    details.</para>
    <para>When a developer goes to apply this sort of patch then we must assume
    responsibility for applying it to our codebase from the IP perspective. So
    we much be comfortable with the providence of the patch and that it is
    clear of potential issues. This is not like a diff where you get to edit it
    and clean up issues before it get applied. The commit is recorded locally
    and the developer will then have a chance to make additional commits to
    address any lingering issues. It is critically important that developers
    applying these sorts of patches are fully aware of what is being committed
    and what they are signing off on.</para>
    <para>To apply the patch the developer will use a command like:</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git am -s 0001-353563-HttpDestinationQueueTest-too-slow.patch
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>Providing it applies cleanly there will now be a commit in their
    local copy and they can either make additional commits or push it out. The
    '-s' option attaches a 'Signed By: ' line to the commit with the developers
    commit information. This is required, without it the commit should be
    rejected by the eclipse git server as not valid. There is an update hook in
    place that validates that either the commit or signed by fields are in fact
    eclipse committers authorized to commit to the repository.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="git-ammend">
    <title>Git Amend</title>
    <para>Alternatively, for troublesome patches that do not seem to apply
    cleanly with git am, you can use git commit --amend to modify the author
    and signoff the commit. For example:</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git checkout -b patch
$ git apply john-doe.patch
$ git commit -a -m "<Original commit message from John Doe>"
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>At this point the patch is committed with the committer's name on a
    local branch</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git commit --amend --author "John Doe <john.doe@who.com>" --signoff
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>Now the patch has the right author and it has been signed off</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git checkout master
$ git merge patch
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>Now the local branch has been merged into master with the right
    author</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git branch -d patch
$ git push
]]>
    </screen>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="gerrit-for-contributors">
    <title>Gerrit for Contributors</title>
    <para>Prepare yourself for using gerrit by following the steps described
    here: 
    <link xl:href="https://git.eclipse.org/r/Documentation/user-upload.html">
    https://git.eclipse.org/r/Documentation/user-upload.html</link></para>
    <para>Then clone the jetty-project:</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git clone ssh://git.eclipse.org:29418/jetty/org.eclipse.jetty.project
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>
    <emphasis>Stop.</emphasis>Make sure you have a bugzilla issue open for the
    change that you want to commit into gerrit for review. Also when you are
    ready to commit your change make sure that your commit starts with the
    bugzilla id. For example your commit should look like this:</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git commit -m "[Bug 343532] fixed issue" <files>
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>Make sure to properly set the changeIds as described here: 
    <link xl:href="https://git.eclipse.org/r/Documentation/user-changeid.html">
    https://git.eclipse.org/r/Documentation/user-changeid.html</link></para>
    <para>Make your changes, commit them as usual with git. Once done
    do:</para>
    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$ git push ssh://git.eclipse.org:29418/jetty/org.eclipse.jetty.project HEAD:refs/for/master
]]>
    </screen>
    <para>Note the magic: "HEAD:refs/for/master". Without gerrit will not
    permit you to push.</para>
    <para>Review your changes on your gerrit dashboard: 
    <link xl:href="https://git.eclipse.org/r/#/">
    https://git.eclipse.org/r/#/</link></para>
    <para>Finally get some coffee and relax. You've contributed something to
    jetty, woohooo. :)</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="gerrit-for-committers">
    <title>Gerrit for Committers</title>
    <para>Using gerrit is pretty simple. Once you have logged in you should
    first register your interest in the project repositories you want to be
    notified of patches on. This option is located under your user Settings
    near your name in the upper right hand corner. Click on 'Watched Projects'
    and then start typing 'jetty' into the project name box and it will offer
    completions for the jetty projects.</para>
    <para>Now that you are watching the appropriate projects you should get
    email notifications of commits into gerrit. It is critical that you follow
    strict committer IP process when reviewing commits. Egregious violations of
    this process can result into committer status issues.</para>
    <para>On the top of the screen click My -&gt; Watched Changes for a list of
    the commits available for review. These represent people waiting to have
    their work reviewed. Once you select an issue to review you will see a list
    of changes at the bottom, click on these and look over the changes. You can
    have a dialog back and forth with the user through the comments on the
    patch. Providing they used the ChangeId setup correctly they will be able
    to issue updates to their patch for further review. Once you are happy with
    a review change set click on the Review button. This brings up a screen
    with three important questions.</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Verified</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Have you verified if this patch is acceptable.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Code Review</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>How acceptable is this review change set? Are you willing to
          testitfy that it is good enough or does it bear further
          review.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>IP Clean</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Does this commit follow acceptable IP guidelines? If anything
          looks suspicious then follow up with comments to clarify any
          potential issues. Commits with minor changes to existing classes and
          projects are fine and should reference a corresponding bugzilla id in
          their commit message.</para>
          <para>Completely new features and large contributions require a
          corresponding CQ reference.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>Assuming sufficient approval through the review process there will be
    an option to Review and Submit and the commit will pass through into jetty
    proper. You may also review and comment without submitting so the Review
    button is useful for clearly stating the reviewers comments and concerns
    regarding the three items mentioned above. Multiple reviewers are able to
    collaborate on a given patch as well.</para>
  </section>
</section>
