<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Logging</title>

  <para>You can use Jetty with external logging frameworks, or you can use
  default Jetty logging.</para>

  <para>With any logging framework, all events have a name and a level. The
  name is a Fully Qualified Class Name (FQCN). The logging framework you
  choose determines the level. While the meaning of the levels is pretty much
  the same across logging frameworks, the descriptive identifiers for those
  levels are different.</para>

  <para>We can even pull in another nested layer of paragraphs if we
  want</para>

  <section>
    <title>Logging with External Frameworks</title>

    <para>You can use a logging framework other than the default Jetty Log.
    You use SLF4J as a façade for a logging framework such as logback,
    java.util.logging, or log4j, and all logging events stream to that
    framework. The way you configure the framework determines what you see.
    If, for example, you want to ignore all events below WARN level, or turn
    on FINE/DEBUG level on org.eclipse.jetty.io.nio?, now you can.</para>

    <para>We allow for a dynamic level of logging to be set on the command
    line.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>-Dorg.eclipse.jetty.LEVEL=ERROR</para>

        <para>this enabled a general level of ERROR logging across all of
        jetty</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>-Dorg.eclipse.jetty.sessions.LEVEL=DEBUG</para>

        <para>this enabled a general level of DEBUG logging across all logging
        coming from the sessions packages.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Prior to: 7.4.5</title>

      <para>The system properties used to enable debugging were:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>-Dorg.eclipse.jetty.util.log.DEBUG=true</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Jetty 6</title>

      <para>In Jetty 6, the system properties used to enable debugging
      were:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>-DDEBUG=true</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="sifting-logging.xml" />

  <xi:include href="6/debugging.xml" />
</section>
