<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
	xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title>Logging</title>

	<para>
		You can use Jetty with external logging frameworks, or you can
		use default Jetty logging.
	</para>

	<para>
		With any logging framework, all events have a name and a level.
		The name is	a Fully Qualified Class Name (FQCN). The logging framework
		you choose determines the level. While the meaning of the levels is
		pretty much	the same across logging frameworks, the descriptive
		identifiers for those levels are different.
	</para>

	<para>
		We can even pull in another nested layer of paragraphs if we want
	</para>

	<title>Logging with External Frameworks</title>

	<para>
		You can use a logging framework other than the default Jetty Log.
		You use SLF4J as a façade for a logging framework such as logback,
		java.util.logging, or log4j, and all logging events stream to that
		framework. The way you configure the framework determines what you
		see. If, for example, you want to ignore all events below WARN level,
		or turn on FINE/DEBUG level on org.eclipse.jetty.io.nio?, now you can.
	</para>

	<para>NOTICE: if we change logging once more for some later version, 
	then this part that is no longer relevant can me cut and paste into 
	the same system-properties.xml setup below used using the xinclude to the subdirectory.</para>

	<para>We allow for a dynamic level of logging to be set on the command line.</para>
  
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>-Dorg.eclipse.jetty.LEVEL=ERROR</para>
          <para>this enabled a general level of ERROR logging across all of jetty</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>-Dorg.eclipse.jetty.sessions.LEVEL=DEBUG</para>
          <para>this enabled a general level of DEBUG logging across all logging coming from the sessions packages.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
    <para>NOTICE: now this a minor difference between versions so I would maybe opt to have this render
    into a sort of wiki tip box layout and have larger changes between versions render out to this whole section difference.</para>
	
	<xi:include href="7.2.4-7.5.3/system-properties.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="7.0.0-7.2.3/system-properties.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="6/system-properties.xml"/>

    <para>NOTICE: long story short, if the docs change between versions we decide if its a big change or a little change and follow
    this procedure to capture that change.  If you really want to just do away with the old information at that point, just comment out the xi:include and 
    it wouldn't get picked up, but the old documentation would still linger until someone decides to just delete it.</para>

</section>
